Rishabh Singh

3219 Overland Ave, Apt 8185 Los Angeles, CA - 90034 Ph: (352) 215-7701 rishabh@utopiacompression.com

R&D Scientist (UtopiaCompression Corporation)

Web: https://www.rishabsing.com Github: https://github.com/rish283 linkedin.com/in/rishabh270

I perform research and development tasks involving machine learning, computer vision and uncertainty quantification at UtopiaCompression Corporation to enhance & develop products/platforms related to intelligent vision systems. I completed my PhD at the Computational NeuroEngineering Lab (advisor: Jose C. Principe).

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy in Electrical and Computer Engineering (GPA: 3.71/4)

May 2018 - Dec 2022

University of Florida

Gainesville, USA

Research Areas: Uncertainty Quantification in ML, Kernel & Bayesian Methods, Adaptive Filtering, Time-Series Analysis.

Master of Science in Electrical and Computer Engineering (GPA: 3.71/4)

Aug 2016 - May 2018

University of Florida

Gainesville, USA

College of Engineering Achievement Award for New Engineering Graduate Students (May 2016 — May 2017)

Coursework: Deep Learning, Big Data Ecosystems, Machine Learning for Time Series, Pattern Recognition,

Noise in Linear Systems, Image Processing and Computer Vision, Quantum Information Science.

Bachelor of Science in Electrical and Electronics Engineering (GPA: 8.46/10)

Aug 2010 - May 2014

Vellore, India

Vellore Institute of Technology RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

UtopiaCompression Corporation

Jan 2023 — Present

Research and Development Scientist:

Los Angeles, USA

- Performing research and engineering tasks to develop and enhance the company's sense and avoid (SAA) platform: a lightweight package for unmanned aircraft systems to navigate in the presence of cooperative and non-cooperative aircraft for use in both military and civilian theatres
- My work focuses on uncertainty quantification and machine learning methods to make the SAA pipeline more robust.
- My responsibilities in general also include improving the company's current algorithms, writing, evaluation and testing code, and aiding technology transition into US government and commercial markets.

University of Florida Aug 2017 — Dec 2022

PhD Candidate and Research Assistant - Computational NeuroEngineering Lab (CNEL):

Gainesville, USA

- Developed and formulated a *physics inspired uncertainty decomposition framework* (capable of single-shot estimation of uncertainty) for data and deep learning (neural network) models by leveraging kernel methods. [paper link]
- Elucidated, through rigorous comparative analysis, many practical advantages of the framework over conventional iterative uncertainty quantification techniques like approximate *Bayesian and ensemble approaches* for both classification and regression problems on benchmark datasets under challenging scenarios like test-set *data distributional shifts* (Models: LeNet, ResNet, VGG. Datasets: MNIST, K-MNIST, CIFAR-10).
- Implemented and analyzed the uncertainty framework against the state-of-the-art for uncertainty quantification of *semantic* segmentation networks (Models: Segnet, FCN-8, PSP-NET, U-NET. Datasets: CamVid, Cityscapes (ongoing)) and for quantifying transfer learning uncertainty between learning models.
- Developed Hierarchical Linear Dynamical System (HLDS) architectures for video game *action sequence segmentation* (DARPA project), *dynamic texture synthesis* and *speech phoneme recognition*.

Aventusoft LLC May 2020 — Aug 2020

Research Scientist Intern

Boca Raton, USA

- Aventusoft LLC is a research startup that develops *medical devices for high-value cardiac assessments* by analyzing heart valve movements. I worked with the *HEMOTAG* device (link), the flagship product of Aventusoft for diagnosing and managing heart failure assessments. My contributions included the following:
- Implemented *deep learning algorithms for detecting anomalies and fiducial points/events in Electrocardiography (ECG)* time-series data as part of a downstream task of arrhythmia detection. The work was incorporated into the HEMOTAG product.
- Tested and validated algorithm's performance on benchmark ECG datasets such as MIT-DB, European ST-T and PhysioNet.
- Collaborated with the research team to discuss and suggest future research work to improve the HEMOTAG technology, specifically to tackle issues involving interpretability of AI algorithms when implemented on medical time-series data.

Jump Trading LLC Oct 2018 — March 2019

Informal Research Collaboration

Chicago, USA (remote)

• Worked with a team in Jump Trading (a high-frequency algorithmic trading firm: link) to test our proposed kernel based algorithm (inspired by Stratonovich's optimal filtering theory) for high speed financial time-series data forecasting.

· Got exposed to many theoretical challenges and practical difficulties in the modeling of financial data.

Vellore Institute of Technology Undergraduate Researcher

Jan 2013 — May 2014

Vellore, India

- Collaborated with a team of 40 members (Team Ojas) to build an electric car for Formula Student (FS) competition, UK (July, 2013). Worked with high voltage electrical systems. Collaborated with the mechanical engineering team to research appropriate motor ratings, type of motors, battery power and management system required to achieve target vehicle performance levels.
- Performed a comparative analysis of induction motor *dynamic braking* schemes using *MATLAB* and *Simulink* as part of an independent research work with a course professor. Work resulted in a publication (paper link).

RELEVANT PUBLICATIONS

- Singh, R. & Principe, J.C. (2022). A Physics inspired Functional Operator for Model Uncertainty Quantification in the RKHS. under review at IEEE Transactions of Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (PAMI). [paper link]
- Singh, R. & Principe, J.C. (2022). Quantifying Model Uncertainty for Semantic Segmentation using Operators in the RKHS. under review.[paper link]
- Singh, R. & Principe, J.C. (2022). Robust Dependence Measure using RKHS based Uncertainty Moments and Optimal Transport. under review.[paper link]
- Hssayeni, Murtadha; Andalib, Arash; Singh, R.; Pava, Diego; Li, Kan; Chait, Robert & Kale, Kaustubh. (2022). ECG Fiducial Points
 Localization Using a Deep Learning Model. under review (related to work done at Aventusoft during internship).
- Singh, R. & Principe, J.C. (2021). Toward a Kernel-based Uncertainty Decomposition Framework for Data and Models. Neural Computation 2021; 33 (5): 1164–1198. [paper link]
- Principe, J.C. & Singh, R. (2022). Functional Operators in RKHS for Epistemic Uncertainty Quantification in Machine Learning.
 LION16: The 16th Learning and Intelligent Optimization Conference.
- Singh, R. & Principe, J.C. (2020). Time Series Analysis using a Kernel based Uncertainty Decomposition Framework. Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence (UAI) 2020. [paper link]
- Singh, R.; Yu, S., & Principe, J.C. (2020). Composite Dynamic Texture Synthesis using Hierarchical Linear Dynamical System. 2020 IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing. [paper link]
- Singh, R. & Principe, J.C. (2019). A New Uncertainty Framework for Stochastic Signal Processing. arXiv preprint arXiv:1904.13038 (2019). [paper link]
- Singh, R. & Principe, J.C. (2018). Correntropy Based Hierarchical Linear Dynamical System for Speech Recognition. In proceedings of 2018 International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN).[paper link]
- Singh, R.; Li, K. & Principe, J.C. (2018). Nearest-Instance-Centroid-Estimation Linear Discriminant Analysis. In proceedings of 2018 IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing.[paper link]

TALKS

- Invited Talk: A Functional Operator for Model Uncertainty Quantification in the Reproducing Kernel Hilbert Space: Machine Learning Group, UIT Arctic University of Norway.
- Contributed Talk: A Quantum Theory Inspired Framework for Uncertainty Quantification: *IEEE International Conference on Data Science and Advanced Analytics (DSAA)*. Speaker: Jose C. Principe (Distinguished Professor, University of Florida).
- **Contributed Talk:** Making Deep Neural Networks Transparent by Information Theory: *Presentation at Microsoft*. Speaker: Shujian Yu (Associate Professor, UIT Arctic University of Norway).

ACADEMIC POSITIONS

Research Assistant Aug 2017 — Dec 2022

Computational NeuroEngineering Lab (CNEL), University of Florida

Gainesville, USA

• Job: Uncertainty quantification in machine learning, Grants: DARPA - FA9453-18-1-0039, ONR - N00014-21-1-2345.

Teaching Assistant

Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, University of Florida

Jan 2022 - May 2022 Gainesville, USA

• Course: *Machine Learning for Time Series (Instructor: Jose C. Principe)* - Theory of adaptation with stationary signals, LMS/RLS algorithms, performance measures. Helped clarify concepts, grade assignments, develop curriculum and deliver lectures.

INDUSTRY EXPERIENCE

Research & Development Scientist UtopiaCompression Corporation

Jan 2023 - Present

Los Angeles, USA

Development of sense-and-avoid intelligent vision platform using machine learning and uncertainty quantification.

Research Scientist Intern

May 2020 - Aug 2020

Aventusoft LLC

Boca Raton, USA

• Fiducial point detection in Electrocardiography (ECG) time-series data using deep learning for arrhythmia detection.

Assistant Manager
Aug 2014 - May 2016

Tata Motors Limited
Pune. India

- Oversaw and improved vehicle assembly line automation systems with respect to safety, maintenance and productivity.
- Achieved top 10% employee performance rating in my department.

SKILLS

Programming Python, ROS (robot operating system), MATLAB, LaTeX, Linux Command Line.

Python Libraries Scikit-learn, Pandas, NumPy, Keras, TensorFlow.

Skills Data structures & algorithms, ML/DL algorithms, Bayesian & ensemble methods, kernel methods.